<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
 *
 * This help file was generated from group_by.sci using help_from_sci().
 *
 -->

<refentry version="5.0-subset Scilab" xml:id="group_by" xml:lang="en"
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
          xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
          xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
          xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
          xmlns:scilab="http://www.scilab.org"
          xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>group_by</refname>
    <refpurpose>A function to perform a group by operation. This function groups data according to the unique values in the target column of the data, splits the data according to those groups and applies a function to the split data.</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>


<refsynopsisdiv>
   <title>Syntax</title>
   <synopsis>
   [outputs] = group_by(header, data, sheader, sdata, target_column, fun_name)
   
   </synopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsection>
   <title>Parameters</title>
   <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>header:</term>
            <listitem><para>  m x 1 vector of headers for numeric data</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>data:</term>
            <listitem><para>    n x m matrix of numeric data, with matrix of column vectors</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>sheader:</term>
            <listitem><para> p x 1 matrix of corresponding headers for string/text data</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>sdata:</term>
            <listitem><para>   n x p matrix of string/text data with data as column vectors</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>target_column:</term>
            <listitem><para> Column on which to group the data and calculate the relevant statistics</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>fun_name:</term>
            <listitem><para> function by which to aggregate the data, the options are "mean", "sum", "min", "max", "stdev" and "count"</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>output:</term>
            <listitem><para> structure containing grouped data for each matrix column, and the corresponding headers and unique groups.</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
</refsection>

<refsection>
   <title>Description</title>
   <para>
If the data is provided in an n x m matrix, and the group volumn has p unique groups. The output of this function contains the result of applying the desired function to the split groups.
A structure with the following fields is returned:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>data: The result of applying the function to the grouped data, a p x m matrix</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>header: The header data for the data, a 1 x m matrix</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>rows: The unique groups which the data was split into and aggregated, a 1 x p matrix</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>group: a structure with fields of the unique groups, each containing a row vector of data corresponding to the header data</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
   </para>
   <para>
</para>
</refsection>
</refentry>
